Okay, בוקר טוב. Boker Tov. Today's דף daf is נ"ד, Nun-Daled, 54,
but we pick up on נ"ג עמוד ב', Nun-Gimmel Amud Bet, and
the discussion is understanding the משנה Mishnah as to the two positions,
one about מעשר שני Maaser Sheni and one about הקדש. Hekdesh. By
מעשר שני, Maaser Sheni, Rabbi Meir says you can never use it
to marry a woman because it is ממון גבוה, Mammon Gavoah, it's
not yours. Rabbi Yehuda says in principle you can, but it won't
work in a case of שוגג, shogeg, when you're unwitting. So שוגג
shogeg makes it worse. Similarly, in a case of הקדש, Hekdesh, we
have Rabbi Meir saying that if you try to marry a woman
with הקדש, Hekdesh, if you do it knowingly that it's הקדש, Hekdesh,
it works, unwittingly it doesn't work. So we have to explain Rabbi
Yehuda says reversal, we'll bracket Rabbi Yehuda for a minute. So we
have to explain why Rabbi Meir or why by מעשר שני Maaser
Sheni שוגג shogeg is worse according to Rabbi Yehuda, and by הקדש,
Hekdesh, מזיד meizid is worse according to Rabbi Meir. So the statement
was that in one of them, the woman doesn't want had she
known, she wouldn't have wanted so it's in error, and in the
other one the man wouldn't both of them wouldn't have wanted had
they known and that's in error. So which is which? So the
first answer that the גמרא Gemara said was by Rabbi Yirmiyah was,
well, it makes sense that מעשר שני Maaser Sheni is the one
that she wouldn't have wanted had she known because she would have
have a שלעפ schlep up to ירושלים. Yerushalayim. But him, what does
he care? If he's willing to get you know, if he would
accept מעשר שני Maaser Sheni and she'll take it to ירושלים, Yerushalayim,
he'd be happy to have her married with מעשר שני. Maaser Sheni.
So with מעשר שני Maaser Sheni the only problem is that had
she known she wouldn't have wanted it. Whereas by הקדש, Hekdesh, neither
of them would have wanted it because had they realized it was
הקדש, Hekdesh, if either of them had realized it was הקדש, Hekdesh,
they would realize that they were doing the sin of מעילה Meilah
and they wouldn't have wanted to have doing to do it. So
that's why הקדש Hekdesh doesn't work because if it's שוגג shogeg because
neither of them would have wanted it. And רש"י Rashi says the
difference to know whether it's who wouldn't have wanted it had they
known is who do you have to ask? Because might you know
in general you know you wonder when you say these rules are
they blanket rules or can you reassess case by case? So if
this is based on a presumption of טעות, to'us, ask the parties
who might be in טעות to'us and if they tell you they
don't mind maybe it would be okay. Anyway, so that's the answer
of Rabbi Yirmiyah that by הקדש, Hekdesh, by מעשר שני Maaser Sheni
she wouldn't have wanted, by הקדש Hekdesh neither of them would have
wanted had they known. So now the גמרא Gemara picks up in
the beginning of in the middle of נ"ג עמוד ב'. Nun-Gimmel Amud
Bet. So we pick up with Rabbi Yaakov, it's about 12
lines down, line starts with the word ורבי יעקב. VeRabbi Yaakov. So
let's do it. Rabbi Yaakov,
so again we what does it mean קידושין kiddushin according to Rabbi
Yehuda with מעשר שני Maaser Sheni where we because מעשר שני Maaser
Sheni is your own ממון mammon and if you know what you're
doing then it works. But she wouldn't have wanted it? No, but
she knows, מזיד meizid means everybody knows. Okay, שוגג shogeg means nobody
knows, מזיד meizid means everybody knows. Does it mean he knew and
she no, no, no, no, we're presuming the knowledge level is the
same across the board. Wait, and the two and that also matters
who you say is in error because if one of them doesn't
and the other does, then it matters who would have a problem
with it. Yes, though yeah, just again the two neither of them
would want הקדש Hekdesh because it's חילול הקדש. chillul Hekdesh. Yeah, they
don't want to be עובר over on being violated הקדש Hekdesh on
מעילה Meilah and being מוציא motzi the הקדש Hekdesh לחולין. lechullin. Okay,
so that's the first answer. Again picking up נ"ג עמוד ב', Nun-Gimmel
Amud Bet, Rabbi Yaakov about 12-15 lines down, beginning of line. Rabbi
Yaakov אמר איפכא מסתברא, amar ipcha mistabra, the opposite makes sense. מי
לא איכא למימר mi lo ika lemeimar מעשר, Maaser, you could say
the following. By מעשר, Maaser, neither of them would have wanted had
they known. Why? אי לא ניחא לה משום טרחא דאורחא, iy lo
nicha lah mishum tircha de'orcha, she wouldn't have wanted because she would
had a שלעפ schlep ירושלים, Yerushalayim, ואי לא ניחא ליה ve'iy lo
nicha leh and he wouldn't have wanted to give her מעשר שני
Maaser Sheni had he known, משום אונסא דאורחא, mishum onsa de'orcha,
because of his liability. Now what does that mean if it got
lost on the way? What does it mean his liability? He gave
it to her, she owns it. So רש"י Rashi first has an
interesting discussion that well maybe since she can't eat it until she
gets to ירושלים, Yerushalayim, she wouldn't be מקודשת mekudeshes until she successfully
got to ירושלים Yerushalayim and it would be worth something. So if
it would have gotten lost along the way then she wouldn't be
מקודשת mekudeshes in the end. So תוספות Tosfos and רש"י Rashi is
not thrilled with that, תוספות Tosfos rejects it completely. He says no
everything indicates that she's married right away, it doesn't matter what happens
afterwards. But רש"י Rashi says what משום אונסא דאורחא mishum onsa de'orcha
means is, she's going to come back to him and she's going
to be angry at him. You gave me this, I was only
able to eat it in ירושלים, Yerushalayim, it got lost, you know
I had a שלעפ schlep there and by the time I got
there it had rotted, you know give give me pay me give
me something else.
So she'll just so you so so because he wouldn't have wanted
to have give her something even if even if legally he wouldn't
have been liable, he wouldn't have wanted to have given her something
that she would only be able to benefit from after she brought
it to ירושלים Yerushalayim and then it would be possible something would
go wrong and she could have a legitimate complaint against him. Okay,
so therefore had he known, had either of them known it was
מעשר שני Maaser Sheni they wouldn't have wanted. He because of the
שלעפ schlep and him because he didn't want to have to hear
about the שלעפ. schlep. Okay, so that's why neither of them would
have wanted it. Okay, now however one minute. אלא הקדש, ella Hekdesh,
exactly, אלא הקדש ella Hekdesh by הקדש, Hekdesh, בשלמא אי לא ניחא
לה, bishlama iy lo nicha lah, we get why she wouldn't have
wanted had she known it was הקדש. Hekdesh. Neither of them would
have wanted it. It was they wouldn't have wanted it; him because
of the שלעפ schlep and him because he didn't want to have
to hear about the שלעפ. schlep. Okay, so that's why, so that's
why neither of them would have wanted it. Okay, now, however, one
minute, אלא הקדש ela hechdeish by הקדש. hechdeish. How do you navigate?
Exactly. אלא הקדש ela hechdeish by הקדש. hechdeish. בשלמא איהי לא ניחא
לה, bishlama eehee lo nicha lah,
we get why she wouldn't have wanted השתנות הקדש, hishtannus hechdeish, דנפחל
הקדש על ידה, di nifchal hechdeish al yadash,
she wouldn't have wanted to be a party for causing הקדש, hechdeish,
for doing מעילה me'ila and causing הקדש hechdeish to be violated and
go out to חולין. chullin. אלא איהו מאי לא ניחא ליה, ela
eehu mai lo nicha lay,
why would he not have wanted it? Which is funny, why? דנפקא
איתתא ממילא, de'nafka itatta mimeila,
because it's like, you know, it's like, oh, well, I mean, I
wouldn't have wanted to willingly violate הקדש, hechdeish, but if I accidentally
violated it and it turned out I was able to marry a
woman and I didn't have to spend my own money, whoops, it
was הקדש, hechdeish, all right, what's so bad? I wasn't intentionally sinning
and I managed to save myself the money of buying a ring,
which is pretty funny, like you really want an עבירה aveira of
מעילה בשוגג me'ila b'shogeg to your credit there? But okay, maybe. I
mean, and you know, he got some benefit from the fact that
he was using הקדש. hechdeish. He didn't have to spend his own
money. So the first answer definitely seems more compelling, that by מעשר
ma'aser it's fundamentally her issue, by הקדש hechdeish it's both of their
issue, but רב יצחק Rav Yitzchak is saying it could be the
reverse. Okay, let's just keep on going a little bit further. Okay,
okay. Now the גמרא Gemara says like this. בעי מיניה רבא מרב
חסדא, ba'ei minei Rava mei'Rav Chisda, so that's the end of the
question of whose problem it was. But bottom line is the reason
it doesn't work in one of those cases of שוגג, shogeg, once
according to רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, once according to רבי מאיר, Rabbi
Meir, is we said had they known they wouldn't have wanted to
go forward. Okay, now. בעי מיניה רב חייא בר אבין מרב חסדא.
במכר מאי? ba'ei minei Rav Chiya bar Avin mei'Rav Chisda b'mecher mai?
Now
if רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir is saying like we assume the רבי
ירמיה's Rabbi Yirmeya explanation that it doesn't work when he didn't realize
it was הקדש hechdeish because he wouldn't have wanted to have... Oh,
I'm sorry, I'm sorry.
משום דלא הוה ידע דנפקא
לחולין. mishum d'lo hava yada d'nafka l'chullin. I'm sorry, I'm sorry. בעי
מיניה רבא מרב חסדא, ba'ei minei Rava mei'Rav Chisda, אשה
אינה מתקדשת, isha eina miskadeshes,
thank you. The woman we said is not married in a case
of שוגג shogeg by הקדש, hechdeish, and we're going to presume רבי
ירמיה's Rabbi Yirmeya explanation because had either of them known, but we're
going to focus on him, had he known, he wouldn't have wanted
to have spent הקדש hechdeish money. You don't want to do an
עבירה. aveira. So had he known, so the transaction was בטעות. b'ta'us.
It's not like I accidentally ate טריפה treifa and you could say
I didn't eat טריפה. treifa. Here, because I wouldn't have wanted to
do it, a transaction doesn't take effect if there's not the right
דעת. da'as. So since it was בטעות, b'ta'us, we say the transaction
never took place and she's not married. So
מעות מהו שיצאו לחולין? ma'os mahu she'yeitz'u l'chullin? Fine, she's not married.
But at the end of the day, he gave her money which
in his mindset he wanted her to possess, she took possession of
it, so would we say that the fact that they wouldn't have
wanted to do it means that there was no מעילה me'ila and
the money didn't go out to
חולין, chullin, or do we say no, the fact that at least
on the surface of it they were taking הקדש hechdeish money makes
it an act of מעילה? me'ila? And מעילה me'ila means it goes
to חולין. chullin.
Well, yes, but only if you actually misuse it. But what we're
saying now is, if we said that had he known he wouldn't
have wanted to and it was בטעות, b'ta'us, so he never misused
it. He never did a transaction with it. Right? He wound up
giving a woman money that was never in the end spent for
קידושין kiddushin because there was a טעות ta'us that was present. So
he never actually spent הקדש. hechdeish. So we're about to get to
that. Okay, one thing at a time. Okay, so if that's true
that it doesn't work because it's בטעות, b'ta'us, then it was בטעות,
b'ta'us, there was no transaction. If there was no transaction, he didn't
misuse הקדש hechdeish money. Or do we say no, no, since at
the surface level they were trying to and the way it appeared
was he was misusing, even though הלכתא-ly halachta it didn't take effect,
that's still an act of מעילה? me'ila? That's the question. Let's see
the answer. אמר ליה אשה אינה מתקדשת מעות היכי יצאו לחולין? amar
lay isha eina miskadeshes ma'os heichi yeitz'u l'chullin? What? If a woman
isn't married, so then the transaction never took place. So all that
took place was one, you know, was it switched hands? But there
was no legal act, there was no taking of possession that happened.
So therefore, since no transaction took place, how could that be an
act of מעילה? me'ila? Okay, the money was, you know, it was
given from the man's hand to the woman's hand, but it wasn't
actually taken possession of by the woman. So therefore there cannot be
an act of מעילה. me'ila. So then the גמרא Gemara asks the
next obvious question. So according to that, there will never be מעילה
בשוגג me'ila b'shogeg by misusing הקדש hechdeish funds. Any time I misuse
הקדש hechdeish funds, we'll say had I known I wouldn't have wanted
to have done the transaction and the transaction therefore was always void
and there was no מעילה. me'ila. So that's the next question of
the גמרא. Gemara. I'm glad you anticipated it. בעי מיניה רב חייא
בר אבין מרב חסדא ba'ei minei Rav Chiya bar Avin mei'Rav Chisda.
במכר מאי? b'mecher mai? What would you say if you were trying
to buy a car with הקדש hechdeish money and you didn't know?
Would you say there would be no מעילה? me'ila? אמר ליה אף
במכר לא קנה. amar lay af b'mecher lo kanah.
Yes, I would say the same thing. Okay, it was unwitting. Had
you known you wouldn't have wanted to do it, so it was
not an actual act of sale, right? It was not a good
transaction. Transaction requires דעת, da'as, the desire to make it happen, and
if there was a substantive fact that you weren't aware of, that
had you been aware of you wouldn't have done the transaction, so
it was not a good sale and therefore there's no מעילה. me'ila.
So now the גמרא, Gemara, one minute, so now the גמרא Gemara
asks the obvious question: if you spend הקדש hechdeish money without knowing,
the purchase is void, so how can there ever be מעילה me'ila
with misuse of הקדש hechdeish funds?
spending money and about changing ownership of money, but when it's actually
about use. If I take הקדש hekdesh oil and I rub it
on my skin, right, or take הקדש hekdesh food and I eat
it, that's מעילה. me'ilah. But normally we understand that
מעילה me'ilah is בשוגג. b'shogeg. בשוגג. b'shogeg. But normally we understand that
classic מעילה me'ilah is I misuse הקדש hekdesh funds not realizing it's
הקדש. hekdesh. And now what we're saying is you would never actually
have spent the money. You might have misplaced הקדש hekdesh funds because
I gave it to the storekeeper and I don't know what the
storekeeper did with it, so the money somehow got lost in the
system, it got misplaced, but it never got misused, it never was
taken possession by somebody else. Okay? So let's take a look. So
the גמרא gemara says,
okay, איתיביה, eiseivei, I'll ask you on this: if that's true, there
will never be מעילה. me'ilah. And here we have a ברייתא braita
that teaches חנווני כבעל הבית דברי רבי מאיר. chanvani k'baal habayit, divrei
Rabbi Meir.
Now this is all within the position of רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir,
right? Because so you have to ask from רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir.
It's רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir who says בשוגג b'shogeg it's not the
woman isn't married because the sale didn't go through, so we're presuming
that within רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir הקדש hekdesh misused בשוגג, b'shogeg, the
transaction never takes effect, there would never be מעילה. me'ilah. So we're
going to ask the question from within רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir. Here's
the ברייתא braita teaches: חנווני כבעל הבית דברי רבי מאיר. chanvani k'baal
habayit, divrei Rabbi Meir. רבי יהודה אומר חנווני כשולחני. Rabbi Yehuda omer
chanvani k'shulchani.
Now what's the case? The case is like this: I have הקדש
hekdesh money in my possession, okay, I forgot it was הקדש, hekdesh,
okay, it's בשוגג. b'shogeg. I go ahead and I give it to
Michael to watch for me for safekeeping. If he's just a normal
בעל הבית, baal habayit, a homeowner, so he has no presumption he
knows he can't use it, whether I gave it to him in
a sealed up package in a sealed up like purse or whether
I gave it to him loose, he knows he's not supposed to
use it and if he uses it then that's his choice, his
doing and he would do מעילה me'ilah not me. None of us
know that it's הקדש. hekdesh. Let's say however Michael here is a
money changer. Okay? If I give a money changer money to hold
for me, if I give it to him in a bound up
purse he knows hands off. If I give him loose money to
hold for me, the presumption is he's able to use that, it's
loose, I know what his business is, he's able to use that
to in his business and he'll just repay me other funds. So
in that case if he goes ahead and I gave him loose
money and he used it, I'm being מועל mo'el because basically that's
essentially like I've authorized him to use that money and if it
gets spent I'm being מועל. mo'el. And then the debate is, is
that clear, yes? Okay, the debate of רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir and
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda is, let's say Michael is not a normal
homeowner and he's not a money changer, he is a storekeeper. Storekeepers
also like to have some loose change available when they're making change
for people and I gave him loose funds. So is and then
he goes ahead and he uses that to make change for people,
okay, is that seen if I've implicitly authorized him and I'm the
one who's מועל, mo'el, or is that seen like no, as long
as you're not a money changer, just hold on to the money
for me, don't use it, and if he chooses to use it,
he's מועל. mo'el. That's the debate of רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir and
רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, but this is all בשוגג. b'shogeg. And רבי
מאיר Rabbi Meir is taking a position here, so it's clear that
רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir holds that misuse of הקדש hekdesh funds בשוגג
b'shogeg is מעילה. me'ilah. Yes? Is this a לפני עיוור lifnei iver
situation, does that play into this at all? It might be, but
it's not relevant, it's not the relevant question. The relevant question by
מעילה me'ilah is, if you remember before,
if I tell my שליח shaliach to do something and we're both
unwitting and he does what I've told him to do or authorized
him to do, I'm the one who's מועל, mo'el, that's like the
one exception to אין שליח לדבר עבירה. ein shaliach l'dvar aveirah. Here's
one thing I don't understand, because the way we've been explaining this
הקדש hekdesh is that they're both at least the way I've been
understanding they're both מועל mo'el when he's before we got to the
full בשוגג b'shogeg and that maybe no one's מועל. mo'el. But that
they're both מועל mo'el in the transaction. I thought it was only
just one party that's מועל. mo'el. Well you're right, meaning in the
case about the one who receives it really isn't מועל, mo'el, it's
really the initiator, that's true. So when we described it before about
the man and the woman, the woman really wasn't a מועל mo'el
but she was a party to the מעילה. me'ilah. She'd rather not
be a party. Exactly. Yeah. Stupid question, when we're talking about loose
funds in contradistinction to
what? Like money in a bound up package that's given over. Yeah
if I'm giving it to you, if I give you like twenty
dollars cash, hold this twenty dollars for me, as opposed to I
give it to you in like a sealed envelope or a wallet,
it's tied up, a tied up bound package, right. Another question is,
it seems to me that we're conflating here the terminology
בשוגג b'shogeg and מזיד mezid what we would usually refer to as
בדעת ובלא דעת. b'da'at u'b'lo da'at. You're right, you're absolutely correct, meaning
בשוגג b'shogeg and מזיד mezid is normally used for questions about willingly
sinning or not willingly sinning whereas here the question is knowingly or
unknowingly. That is true. Okay, so now the גמרא gemara says like
so anyway עד כאן לא קמיפלגי, ad kan lo kamifligi,
until here the debate is only, דמר סבר חנווני כשולחני, d'mar savar
chanvani k'shulchani,
that רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda thinks... at the storekeeper is like the
money changer, and if he spends it, that's my sin because I
should have known he was going to use it. ומר סבר חנוני
כבעל הבית u-mar savar chanvani k'baal habayit
and Rabbi Meir holds that the storekeeper is like the homeowner, and
it's the storekeeper's sin because he shouldn't have used the money even
if it was loose funds.
Okay, אבל דכולי עלמא aval d'chulei alma everybody agrees אם הוציא מעל
im hotzi maal that that מעילה me'ilah is done. Question is, who
did the מעילה, me'ilah, me or the storekeeper? But everybody agrees there's
מעילה me'ilah even if it's the unwitting use of money. So the
גמרא Gemara says, so
that's pretty good evidence, the גמרא Gemara somehow though is going to
get out of it. רבי מאיר לדבריו דרבי יהודה קאמר. Rabbi Meir
l'divrav d'Rabbi Yehuda ka'amar. No, Rabbi Meir is only responding within Rabbi
Yehuda's position. לדידי l'didi as I'm concerned אם הוציא נמי לא מעל
im hotzi nami lo maal nobody is מועל moel here because the
money just changed hands but nobody actually took possession of it, it
was all בטעות, b'taut, so therefore nobody was מועל. moel. אלא לדידך
ella l'didach but you that you say there's מעילה, me'ilah, אודי לי
מיהא חנוני כבעל הבית odi li miha chanvani k'baal habayit at least
concede to me that in this case the חנוני chanvani is acting
on his
own, he's like a homeowner, he's not sort of doing it with
the authorization of the person who gave him the money. ואמר ליה
v'amar lei he said לא כשלחני, lo k'shulchani, no he's like a
money changer, he does have the right to use it. Meaning, I
can debate with you how I would conceptually the authority given to
a storekeeper even if I disagree in principle with your whole presumption
of how מעילה me'ilah takes effect. It's a weak answer obviously because
obviously it's clear that the implicit buy-in here that you agree that
that's an act of מעילה. me'ilah. But the גמרא Gemara is going
to be working on this for the remainder of today with a
strong position, there'll be another position, there'll be an opposing position, but
a strong approach that according to Rabbi Meir you can never do
מעילה me'ilah when it is unwitting because then the transaction is void
if you're actually talking about a spending of funds as opposed to
a benefiting from an object. Okay, so let's keep on going with
this. אמר רב, amar Rav, so Rav says, חזינו chazinu and here
the גמרא Gemara is going to pull back from this because it's
saying that's way too extreme of a position. חזינו chazinu this is
great language, חזינו על כל צדדים של רבי מאיר. chazinu al kol
tzdadim shel Rabbi Meir. We looked at all of the positions of
Rabbi Meir. We investigated this from all the sides, okay? And we
looked at everything Rabbi Meir ever said. Okay, so we did a
בר אילן Bar Ilan search. ולא מצינו הקדש בשוגג אין מתחלל במזיד
מתחלל. v'lo matzinu hekdesh b'shogeg ein mitchalel b'meizid mitchalel.
We have never found Rabbi Meir saying such an absurd position, okay?
That you, if you misuse הקדש hekdesh funds willingly, it's מעילה me'ilah
but unwittingly it's not מעילה me'ilah because, and here's something important I
want to introduce to explain the debates of Rabbi Meir and Rabbi
Yehuda, the general presumption is that הקדש hekdesh is, that מעילה me'ilah
is בשוגג, b'shogeg, meaning when you bring a קרבן korban of מעילה,
me'ilah, it's clearly בשוגג b'shogeg and number two, the general presumption is
that the only time מעילה, me'ilah, the funds go out to חולין
chullin is when they're misused בשוגג. b'shogeg. When they're misused במזיד b'meizid
you transgress but the funds do not go out לחולין. l'chullin. Now
Rabbi Meir actually is, not quoted here but in a different גמרא,
Gemara, of the position that you actually the funds go out to
חולין chullin even במזיד. b'meizid. Actually תוספות Tosafot quotes it, he says
you could see from a פסוק pasuk Rabbi Meir's idea that מעילה
me'ilah is even במזיד b'meizid from the פרשה parsha of סוטה Sotah
because it says איש כי תשטה אשתו ומעלה בו מעל, ish ki
tisteh ishto u-maala vo maal, so she's knowingly cheating on her husband,
so you could have a concept of מעילה me'ilah willingly. Fine. Rabbi
Meir says even במזיד b'meizid the funds go out to חולין, chullin,
but the general presumption is that the fundamental category of מעילה me'ilah
is בשוגג b'shogeg and Rav is saying it, we have never found
Rabbi Meir ever say that there's only מעילה במזיד me'ilah b'meizid and
that the funds never occurs בשוגג. b'shogeg. That's crazy, that's the opposite
of what we normally assume. So how do you explain the משנה?
mishna? So by the way, let's, I want to just show you,
I mean I hope this doesn't get too confusing, I'm just going
to do this once, okay? If it's too confusing don't do it.
But here's Rabbi Meir and here's Rabbi Yehuda. This is the משנה
mishna by הקדש, hekdesh, okay? And you've got שוגג shogeg and מזיד.
meizid. So Rabbi Meir says בשוגג b'shogeg
no קידושין, kiddushin, right? במזיד b'meizid yes קידושין. kiddushin. Rabbi Yehuda says
the opposite, שוגג shogeg yes, מזיד meizid no. So we haven't really
been investigating Rabbi Yehuda, but let me just tell you in one
sentence what Rabbi Yehuda's position is. You know why במזיד b'meizid there's
no קידושין? kiddushin? Because Rabbi Yehuda takes the normal position that מעילה
בשוגג me'ilah beshogeg the money goes out to חולין. chullin. במזיד b'meizid
it does not go out to חולין. chullin. So when it was
unwitting, the money went out to חולין, chullin, she took possession of
the money, she's the legal owner of the money, I might have
transgressed, but it works. במזיד b'meizid the money didn't go out to
חולין, chullin, it wasn't my money to give, it wasn't hers to
take, it remains הקדש's, hekdesh it doesn't work. That's Rabbi Yehuda. That's
what we normally say by מעילה. me'ilah שוגג shogeg the money goes
out to חולין, chullin, מזיד meizid not. Rabbi Meir
is
the
reverse. Okay, so if you both knew it was הקדש, hekdesh, you
willingly violated, he takes possession of the money, even במזיד bemeizid the
money goes out to חולין. chullin. But why doesn’t it work בשוגג?
b'shogeg So right now we're suggesting for רבי מאיר, Rebbi Meir, there's
never מעילה בשוגג. me'ilah b'shogeg, The money never goes out to חולין,
chullin, there's never מעילה, me'ilah. you didn't want the transaction. But then
that's absurd because that's the exact opposite of what we normally assume
by מעילה. Me'ilah So that's what we have to figure out. Why
he could say במזיד, bemeizid, fine, he thinks the money goes out
to חולין chullin even though that's not the standard, but is he
really going to say there's never מעילה בשוגג? me'ilah b'shogeg? How so,
how are we going to explain why there's no קידושין kiddushin other
than saying there's never מעילה בשוגג me'ila b'shogeg? which seems to be
an absurd position? So after having laid this out in that chart,
could you now just reiterate how does the משנה Mishnah in מעילה
Me'ilah, about the חנוני Chanvani and the שולחני Shulchani apply to or—no,
I don't want to do that with this chart. I mean, that's
basically saying that somebody is spending the money בשוגג beshogeg? and it
goes out and it goes out to חולין chullin and then it
depends right? Both parties are unwitting, the money gets spent, מעילה Me'ilah.
takes place, that classic מעילה Me'ilah is בשוגג, beshogeg. and the only
question is whose initiative was it? If somebody was acting on the
authority of the בעל הבית, ba'al habayis, the בעל הבית ba'al habayis
is מועל, mo'el, if he was acting on his own authority he's
מועל. mo'el. But the basic case is—what? So what happens—all that is
within the bottom right? Is within the bottom left. All of that
is within שוגג. shogeg. Meaning, classic מעילה Me'ilah is, I give you
money, you don't know it's הקדש, hekdesh, I don't know it's הקדש,
hekdesh, it gets spent, מעילה Me'ilah takes place. Classic מעילה Me'ilah is
בשוגג. beshogeg? But the discussions of בעל הבית, ba'al habayis, חנוני, Chanvani,
שליח, shaliach, all the only thing that's trying to figure out is,
if you did it on my authorization, I'm מועל. mo'el. If you
did it on your own authority, you're מועל. mo'el. But all of
that, this is classic, this is classic מעילה, Me'ilah okay? This is
classic מעילה Me'ilah is
בשוגג. beshogeg So, רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda says here, 'not יצא לחולין.'
yatza l'chullin. רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir has the חידוש chidush that במזיד
bemeizid is יצא לחולין. yatza l'chullin. Okay, that's a general חידוש chidush
by מעילה. Me'ilah But how could he deny the classic category of
מעילה בשוגג? me'ila b'shogeg And we're trying to claim that he does.
That all those stories about חנוני Chanvani and misuse of money, whatever,
that's not according to רבי מאיר. Rebbi Meir. There's an asymmetry of
דעת, da'at, one is בשוגג, beshogeg one is במזיד. bemeizid. All right,
let's not worry about that. Then the—yes, that comes up in מסכת
מעילה, Maseches Me'ilah, but we're not going to worry about that. So,
okay, אחזינן כל קומי שמי דרבי מאיר ולא מצינו הקדש בשוגג אין
מתחלל במזיד מתחלל. achazeinan kol qumei sheme d’Rebbi Meir v’lo matzinu hekdesh
beshogeg ein mis-challel bemeizid mis-challel. We have never found him taking this
reverse position that it doesn't go out to חולין chullin בשוגג beshogeg,
and it does במזיד. bemeizid. He could say it במזיד, bemeizid, but
then he'd better say it בשוגג beshogeg. as well. So then what's
the פשט p'shat of our משנה? Mishnah? Why is the woman not
married when it's
בשוגג? beshogeg. ומשנתנו U-Mishnasenu is in a very special case. See if
you can buy this answer. בכתונת כהונה שלא בלו. Be-kesones kehuna she-lo
balu. We're talking about הבית? habayis? Okay. It's talking about the בגדי
כהונה bigdei kehuna that were—that had not been worn out. So he
tried, somehow he got access to one of the cloaks of a
כהן, kohen, he was a כהן kohen maybe, and he said, 'you're
married to me with my cloak' and it had not yet worn
out—we'll see why that's relevant in a minute. And then רבי מאיר
Rebbi Meir says, 'Ah, well then if it was בשוגג beshogeg? you're
not מועל.' mo'el. Why? If normally there's מעילה בשוגג? me'ila b'shogeg Because
there's a special exception that you don't transgress מעילה בשוגג me'ila b'shogeg
by בגדי כהונה. bigdei kehuna. Why is there that exception? Let's read
the next line. הואיל וניתנו ליהנות בהם. ho'il v'nitnu lihanis bahem. Since
כהנים kohanim have the permission to benefit from them. Now you might
say you can only benefit from them while they're doing the עבודה,
avodah, but now comes the next line: שלא ניתנה תורה למלאכי השרת.
she-lo nitna Torah l'malachei ha-shares. Such a great line. The תורה Torah
was not given to the heavenly angels. A כהן kohen cannot be
told as soon as the second the עבודה's avodah off, you gotta
strip. And if you left your בגדים begadim on two minutes because
you were talking to your friend after the day of—after the day
had ended, after the gates had been shut, oh, then you're מועל
mo'el because you were wearing your בגד beged two minutes when you
weren't doing the עבודה? avodah? No, the תורה Torah wasn't given to
מלאכי השרת. malachei ha-shares. It's a great line something that's used like
in issues about like do we have to worry about microscopic
bugs, תורה Torah isn't given to מלאכי השרת. malachei ha-shares. It's based
on human standards. And therefore, according to this, there's a general exemption
of מעילה Me'ilah from בגדי כהונה. bigdei kehuna. If you use your
בגדי כהונה bigdei kehuna unwittingly—wittingly would be different—but unwittingly, you're not transgressing
מעילה, Me'ilah, you're given that special allowance, that's the reality of—So someone
if he forgot it's the בגד beged of the בית המקדש, Beis
HaMikdash, שמעילה גביה דהשוגג? she-me'ilah geveiah d'ha-shogeg? Yeah, exactly. That'd be right,
you'd have to like, 'Oh, here's this interesting belt, it just looks
mighty like my regular belt,' I don't know, maybe you found a
belt on the street and he thought, 'Oh, well it's probably יאוש,'
ye'ush, he took possession of the belt, I don't know why, it's
a crazy case. Okay. And that's why he says there's no מעילה
Me'ilah בשוגג, beshogeg, but in general of course there should be מעילה
Me'ilah. בשוגג. beshogeg So now the גמרא Gemara says, okay, let's try
to prove whether that's true about בגדי כהונה. bigdei kehuna. Because if
it already was בלו, balu, then it would already be יצא לחולין?
yatza l'chullin? Well, yeah, that's the next line we're about to—no, the
opposite. We're about to— תא שמע. ta shema. So we're going to,
let's investigate this בגדי כהונה bigdei kehuna thing for a minute. Okay.
כתונות כהונה שבלו, kotonos kehuna shebalu, if you have the the cloak
of the כהונה kehuna that is now worn out and it's sort
of it's put in the you know it's going to be repurposed
or something, it's not going to be worn by the
כהנים kohanim
anymore. מועלין בהם, mo'alin bahem, דברי רבי מאיר. divrei Rabbi Meir. רבי
מאיר Rabbi Meir says that there is מעילה. Me'ilah So the גמרא
Gemara assumes, מאי לאו אפילו לא בלו? mai lav afilu lo balu?
It says worn out, but presumably there wouldn't be a difference between
worn out and not worn out. Now we've already signaled there is
because we characterized the first case by "worn out", but this is
telling us why. What would be the difference? So the גמרא Gemara
says, לא, בלו דוקא. lo, balu davka. No, only if they've worn
out. So it doesn't tell us the difference, but what is the
difference? The difference is the whole reason there was an allowance is
because these are things that you wear. You're wearing them! Once they
stop being worn, then it's just simple property owned by הקדש, hekdesh,
so who knows what הקדש hekdesh will do? They'll sell it, there's
some you know it's some raw material, they'll make it into wicks
for whatever. But but your allowance was only in the context when
they were still usable because then there was a reality that you
were going to have to use them and you had to be
given a certain amount of latitude. Once they stop being usable, they're
standard הקדש hekdesh and you have no allowance. Okay. תא שמע. ta
shema. Now by the way, if that's true, what's the position of
רבי יהודה? Rabbi Yehuda? Because if we are really talking about about
you know בגדי כהונה, bigdei kehuna, and that's why רבי מאיר Rabbi
Meir says there's no transgression בשוגג beshogeg or there's no מעילה, Me'ilah
what does you know what does רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda say? So
רש"י Rashi basically says like a little later but it's a basic
point is that רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda would have to say that
even though there was an allowance, it was a limited allowance. It
wasn't like oh there's no מעילה Me'ilah בשוגג beshogeg? by בגדי כהונה.
bigdei kehuna. There's no מעילה Me'ilah if you wear them too long.
Okay, for that mistake or keeping them on a little bit too
long, there there's no מעילה. Me'ilah, Nobody said if you accidentally give
them to a woman to get married with or do some other
misuse there's no מעילה. Me'ilah Okay, so that's now how we're explaining
the debate in the משנה Mishnah in a very, very limited way.
All right, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this. תא
שמע, מועלין בחדתין ואין מועלין בעתיקין. ta shema, mo'alin bechadatin ve'ein mo'alin
be'atikin. Okay, you are מועל mo'el with new שקלים shekels and not
with old שקלים. shekels. What would happen? You know starting אדר Adar
people would donate their שקל shekel to the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash
for use in the new קרבנות korbanos of the year, the communal
קרבנות korbanos that would be brought in ניסן. Nisan. Okay, and if
you would be late giving your your שקל shekel in, you would
come at different you know and you only gave it later in
the year, it would still go into a box that was said
חדתין, chadatin, new שקל, shekel, and you'd put it in the box
and then next time they took what was called the תרומת הלשכה,
terumas halishka, they took funds from that you know from those from
the donated funds to buy the next round of קרבנות korbanos because
they would do three rounds of buying קרבנות korbanos throughout the
year, at least it would be coming from your funds, your funds
would be part of the communal funds. If however you forgot the
entire year to give your שקל shekel and you showed up in
the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash a year later, then you would give
this year's שקל shekel now but you'd give last year's שקל shekel
in a box marked old שקל, shekel, okay, עתיקין, atikin, old שקל.
shekel. Okay, now what would they do with the old שקל shekel
funds? They wouldn't buy קרבנות. korbanos. What they would do with the
old שקל shekel funds is they would use it for type of
like communal needs as we're going to like building the walls of
the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, building the walls of ירושלים. Yerushalayim. What?
Roads? Not don't think roads, but a little more a little more
well, חומת העיר ומגדלותיה chomas ha'ir umigdaloteha maybe, yeah, yeah, רש"י Rashi
says כל צרכי תיקון העיר. kol tzorchei tikkun ha'ir. Yeah, maybe roads.
Okay, at types of things of putting it to municipal ירושלים Yerushalayim
type of needs and מקדש Mikdash types of needs. Now because of
that, here's the thing. If I'm using that money to buy a
wall, to build a wall of ירושלים, Yerushalayim, what are you going
to do once that wall is built? What's that wall? You're going
to sit on it, you're going to you're going to get shade
from it, you're going to be נהנה neheneh from it, right? So
okay, that's a type of a thing like the בגדי כהונה bigdei
kehuna in the sense that funds are being spent and presumably there's
some right to use them in that capacity. Okay, so does that
mean that they're totally excluded from laws of מעילה? Me'ilah That's sort
of the analogy we're making. Let's take a look. Okay, so meaning
before you spent it, the old שקלים shekels are they excluded? Is
that the question? Well these these old שקלים shekels are going to
go towards communal needs. Okay, so does that mean that because there
are certain uses that are allowed from it for a personal you
know people will benefit from it, that gives that it's they're completely
excluded from מעילה? me'ilah. Let's say in the but in the end
I don't use it as sitting on a wall, I accidentally took
it and spent it to build I misused it and I bought
a car with it or something, right? Is it completely excluded from
מעילה me'ilah, once there are certain allowances given? תא שמע, מועלין בחדתין,
ta shema, mo'alin bechadatin, you're מועל mo'el with the new funds because
that's going for קרבנות, korbanos, ואין מועלין בעתיקין, ve'ein mo'alin be'atikin, not
the old ones which is going for these municipal needs. רבי מאיר
אומר מועלין אף בעתיקין. Rabbi Meir omer mo'alin af be'atikin. No, even
the old ones. שהיה רבי מאיר אומר, shehaya Rabbi Meir omer, רבי
מאיר Rabbi Meir used to say, מועלין בשירי הלשכה, mo'alin beshirei halishka,
you would be מועל mo'el with leftover money from the funds for
the buying of the קרבנות, korbonot, any funds not taken of that
year were called שירי לשכה, sheyarei lishka, the remainder of the funds,
and would be spent on these communal needs, like the last year's
funds are spent on these communal needs. And therefore he says there
is מעילה. me'ilah So we've got a problem. How would you say
there's no מעילה me'ilah. by בגדי כהונה bigdei kehuna even if you
use it to marry a woman, here you have even more allowance
than בגדי כהונה. bigdei kehuna. You're using these money to build the
חומת ירושלים. Chomat Yerushalayim. How can you say that there's מעילה me'ilah.
by it? Shouldn't we say that once you have some allowance, that
gives you a complete פטור ptor from מעילה me'ilah? in this regard?
Like if that's what you're saying by בגדי כהונה. bigdei kehuna. The
old coins are like the frayed בגדים. bgadim. No, the frayed בגדים
bgadim are not going to be used by you. This money, the
old coins, are for something else of the הקדש. hekdesh. They're not
given, so the normal person is not given any allowance to use
them. The old coins are going to be used to build up
the walls, which specifically means that normal people are going to be
able to benefit from them, right? The old בגדים bgadim normal people
don't have a right to benefit from. Nobody has a right. They're
הקדש. hekdesh. Everybody else hands off. So the new בגדים, bgadim, כהנים
kohanim have a right to benefit. The old money, normal people have
a right to benefit from, they're going to be used to build
walls. So if nevertheless there still is מעילה me'ilah? even though there's
going to be a wide range of benefits that are going to
be allowed to people, so how could that be מעילה me'ilah there
when it's misused outside of those parameters and not be מעילה meilah.
by בגדי כהונה? bigdei kehuna? That's the question. Okay, and why would
רבי מאיר Reb Meyer say there's מעילה? meilah נימא הווי ניתנו ליהנות
nema hovei nitnu lehanos לפי שלא ניתנה למלאכי השרת. lefi shelo nittnah
l'malachei hashareis. Let's say that there's no מעילה meilah because you have
right to benefit because Torah wasn't given to heavenly angels. חומת העיר
ומגדלותיה chomat ha'ir umigdaloseha משירי לשכה עשו. mishirei lishka asu. You would
use these funds, and these would be things that normal people would
get benefits from. דתנן, detnan, we saw in a משנה, mishnah, חומת
העיר ומגדלותיה chomat ha'ir umigdaloseha וכל צורכי העיר vechol tzorchei ha'ir משירי
לשכה. mishirei lishka. So and therefore even more than the בגדי כהונה.
bigdei kehuna. If you think that there's no מעילה meilah by בגדי
כהונה bigdei kehuna even any type of misuse, then it should certainly
be true by שירי לשכה. sheyarei lishka. So the גמרא Gemara says,
alright, לא תימא רבי מאיר אלא אימא רבי יהודה. lo teima Reb
Meyer ella eima Rebbi Yehuda. Take out every רבי מאיר Reb Meyer
that appeared in that ברייתא braisa and replace it with רבי יהודה.
Rebbi Yehuda. רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda is the one, the same way
we're claiming that רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda in our משנה mishnah says
there is מעילה meilah by בגדי כהונה bigdei kehuna בשוגג beshogeg when
you use it outside of the parameters of the special allowance that
was given. So he would say there's also מעילה meilah by the
שירי לשכה sheyarei lishka when you use it outside of the parameters
for what it's earmarked for, okay? So obviously we're on a real,
real stretch. We tried to say our entire משנה mishnah is talking
about a hyper-special case of בגדי כהונה, bigdei kehuna, and even though
there's clear evidence that רבי מאיר Reb Meyer feels that in those
types of cases there would be מעילה meilah once even though you
have certain allowances, there'd be מעילה meilah? when you go beyond those
allowances, we're reversing רבי מאיר Reb Meyer with רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda
to keep everything within this frame. What would רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda
be מועל, moel, the שירי לשכה? sheyarei lishka? When you use it
outside of the allowances. You're... yes, he would not disagree, he would
not say a כהן kohen has to strip the second the עבודה
avodah is over. You do have a certain amount of latitude. You
do have, if I'm going to use the money to build the
חומת העיר, chomat ha'ir, you have the right to sit on it,
okay? But if you accidentally, I don't know, a boulder falls off
of the wall and you go ahead and you take it and
I don't know and you don't realize it belongs to the בית
המקדש beis hamikdash and you build it in your house, you do
something that's outside of the parameters that were allowed, he would say
that would be מעילה. meilah So why, so what's interesting to me
about that position of רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda now is that he
sort of expands as it were even physically the influence of the
מקדש mikdash outside of the מקדש. mikdash. המגדל העיר hamigdal ha'ir has
a kind of קדושה kedusha to it. Well, right, yes, correct. I
mean that's in general, and we're going to see that. That's in
general. I mean look, it's a hard concept בכלל. bechol. You really
think that you're going to go out and build a wall of
a city and keep saying but this is still הקדש, hekdesh, you
can only use it this way and not that way? I mean
that's one thing to say it about בגדי כהונה, bigdei kehuna, another
thing to say... I understand it's a... but anyway, yes, it's a
pretty... I got it, I got it. If there's any place to
say that there's no מעילה, meilah it would be by... it would
be by חומת העיר, chomat ha'ir, not by בגדי כהונה. bigdei kehuna.
Is there any מעילה meilah now? Meaning like, you know, like what
about... yeah, I don't know. Yeah, I don't know. That's an interesting
question, like if anybody raises that issue. I mean I think right
now the walls were all built by what's-his-name, like in... no, I
know, but I'm saying maybe like some of the rubble there and
they use it for building. Yeah, it's a good question. Yeah, I
think probably both people פשוט pashut in מחילה, mechilah, there's other ways
in which the הקדש hekdesh goes off especially after it's been conquered
and destroyed, yeah. How do you know which stones were from... that's
what Michael's just asked you, yeah. That's why I think you have
to take the position that, you know, you do have an allowance
by... by the חומת העיר. chomat ha'ir. But okay, let's keep on
going. תא שמע, Ta shema, come and hear. דתניא, Detanya, אמר רבי
ישמעאל בר רבי יצחק, Amar Rabbi Yishmael bar Rabbi Yitzchak, אבני ירושלים
שנשרו, Avnei Yerushalayim shenashru, so this is exactly the case, okay? The
stones fell off the wall, מועלין בהן. mo'alin bahen. There still is
מעילה. meilah דברי רבי מאיר. Divrei Rabbi Meir. Again, Rabbi Meir says
there is מעילה. meilah So even something that an allowance was given,
if you go ahead and you go beyond those allowances and build
it in your house, there is מעילה. meilah So how can you
say that Rabbi Meir in our משנה Mishnah says there's no מעילה
meilah. by בגדי כהונה bigdei kehunah because there's a limited allowance, okay?
And a limited allowance means a blanket allowance? You see it doesn't
say that! So the גמרא Gemara says, same answer. לא תימא רבי
מאיר אלא אימא רבי יהודה. Lo tema Rabbi Meir ela eima Rabbi
Yehuda. Fine, let's just change the name. Okay, the גמרא Gemara says,
you see it works like on the election results. If it's Rabbi
Yehuda, ירושלים מי קדשי? Yerushalayim mi kadshi? It can't be Rabbi Yehuda
because now this gets to your question. So now we've got Rabbi
Yehuda saying that there's that your latitude is more limited and that
it's קדוש. kadosh. But we know that Rabbi Yehuda's approach is that
we don't treat the walls of ירושלים Yerushalayim to be קדוש. kadosh.
How do we know that? ותנן, Vetnan, taught in a משנה Mishnah
in נדרים. Nedarim. It's been a while since we did נדרים. Nedarim.
כאימרא כדירים כעצים כאישים. Ke'imra kedirim ke'etzim ke'ishim. If you say a
certain object, let's say a loaf of bread, is like something הקדש,
hekdesh, it's אסור בנדר. assur b'neder. Okay? So if you say it's
like a lamb, like it's like the wood that's used on the
you know, like like like on the on the altar, fire of
the altar, כהיכל כמזבח, keheichal kemizbe'ach, like the like you know, like
the sanctum, like the altar, כירושלים, k'Yerushalayim, all of those things are
the נדר. neder. Rabbi Yehuda disagrees. רבי יהודה אומר כל האומר ירושלים
לא אמר כלום. Rabbi Yehuda omer kol ha'omer Yerushalayim lo amar klum.
Using ירושלים Yerushalayim is not a נדר, neder, presumably because ירושלים Yerushalayim
doesn't have the walls don't have קדושה, kedusha, right? I mean it
has a קדושה kedusha but it's not the same type of קדושה
kedusha of the הקדש. hekdesh. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says, וכי
תימא משום דלא אמר כירושלים. Vechi tema mishum dela amar k'Yerushalayim. You'll
say no, no, no, he's not debating the nature of ירושלים. Yerushalayim.
The problem is you didn't say let this be like ירושלים. Yerushalayim.
You just said let this be ירושלים. Yerushalayim. You need the כ,
k, the comparison, to be the keyword to transfer the status or
you know to append to to bring the status apply the status
to this other object. You're saying let this be ירושלים, Yerushalayim, that
doesn't mean anything. But that's not true. That's not his issue. והתניא,
Vehatanya, we taught in a ברייתא, braita, רבי יהודה אומר כל האומר
כירושלים לא אמר כלום. Rabbi Yehuda omer kol ha'omer k'Yerushalayim lo amar
klum. Even if you said let this be like ירושלים Yerushalayim you
didn't do anything because you used the right formula, but ירושלים Yerushalayim
is not a דבר davar that is sanctified בפה, ba'peh, okay, and
therefore it's not good for a נדר. neder. Alright, so you see
that he feels that the walls that are used to build ירושלים
Yerushalayim don't have any קדושה. kedusha. It must be once the שערי
לשכה sha'arei lishkah spent, once there's given latitude, the latitude is basically
given across the board. So again, how can you say that Rabbi
Yehuda takes the מחמיר machmir position in this debate between him and
Rabbi Meir? עד כאן בדבר הקרב בירושלים. Ad kan bedavar hakarev b'Yerushalayim.
He says the only נדר neder is when you say something is
like a sacrifice brought in ירושלים, Yerushalayim, but ירושלים Yerushalayim itself is
not a דבר קדוש. davar kadosh. So the גמרא's Gemara answer again
very not satisfying. תרי תנאי אינו אליבא דרבי יהודה. Trei tannai inu
aliba d'Rabbi Yehuda. Fine, there's a debate of תנאים tannaim about what
Rabbi Yehuda's position is. Some תנאים tannaim think that Rabbi Yehuda feels
that ירושלים Yerushalayim the walls do not have sanctity, and others feel
that according to Rabbi Yehuda the walls do have sanctity and you're
over on מעילה, meilah, but we are still now trying to assert
that rather than taking this to its logical conclusion that Rabbi Meir
says that when it comes to spending funds there's no מעילה meilah
בשוגג, beshogeg? right, which would be the exact opposite of everything we
think is true about מעילה, me'ilah. we're trying to make this an
extremely narrow case of בגדי כהונה bigdei kehunah where there might be
because there's limited allowance there might be broader allowance. The only problem
is that if you look at all the discussions of מעילה me'ilah.
and so on, it seems like that more lenient position is the
Rabbi Yehuda position and that Rabbi Meir is the stricter position and
says that you are that you know that by ירושלים Yerushalayim and
by שערי לשכה sha'arei lishkah and all those things there is מעילה.
me'ilah. But we just keep on reversing the names until it all
works out. Okay, so that's to try to explain this in a
very limited way about בגדי כהונה bigdei kehunah and similar things where
the limited allowance means a broad allowance. But now we're going to
go back to the broader read of Rabbi Meir. Okay, עולא משמיה
דבר פדא, Ulla mishmei d'Bar Padda, so עולא Ulla in the name
of בר פדא Bar Padda goes back to our first read that
Rabbi Meir basically says no מעילה me'ilah by misuse of funds בשוגג.
beshogeg Okay, משמיה דבר פדא אומר אומר היה רבי מאיר, Mishmei d'Bar
Padda omer omer hayah Rabbi Meir, Rabbi Meir used to say, הקדש
במזיד מתחלל בשוגג אין מתחלל. Hekdesh bemeizid hitchallel beshogeg ein hitchallel. Okay,
a minute ago you said חזרנו על כל הצדדים ולא מצינו רבי
מאיר אומר כן, Chazarnu al kol hatzedadim velo matzinu Rabbi Meir omer
ken, I don't care if you לא מצינו, lo matzinu, what do
you mean לא מצינו? lo matzinu? He said it right here! Okay,
yes, this is Rabbi Meir's position. If you misuse funds, it only
goes out לחולין lechullin במזיד. bemeizid. בשוגג beshogeg, it does not go
out לחולין lechullin because the sale is void. בשוגג אין מתחלל. Beshogeg
ein hitchallel. So when do we speak about the idea that there's
מעילה me'ilah, בשוגג? beshogeg. אלא בקרבן בלבד. Ela bekurban bilvad. Only for
bringing a קרבן, korban, the money doesn't go out לחולין. lechullin. Wait
a minute. One minute. וכי מאחר דאין מתחלל. V'chi mei'achar d'ein mischalel.
One minute. If the money doesn't go out לחולין l'chulin and the
sale is void, קרבן במאי מחייב, korban b'mai michayiv, why are you
bringing a קרבן? korban? אלא לאו, Ela lav, here's what we mean.
כי אתא רבין פירש משמיה דבר פדא, Ki ata Ravin peireish mishmei
d'Bar Pada, אמר הכי רבי מאיר, Amar hachi Rabbi Meir, Rabbi Meir
said, הקדש במזיד מתחלל, hekdesh b'meizid mischalel, the money goes out לחולין
l'chulin if you're knowing. בשוגג אין מתחלל, B'shogeg ein mischalel, unknowingly not,
the sale is void and the money doesn't go out לחולין. l'chulin.
ולא אמרו בשוגג מתחלל, V'lo amru b'shogeg mischalel, when would you ever
transgress מעילה me'ilah, בשוגג? beshogeg אלא לעניין אכילה בלבד, Ela l'inyan achila
bilvad, if it were something like I accidentally ate food of הקדש,
hekdesh, or I anointed myself with oil of הקדש, hekdesh, or I
used הקדש hekdesh oil for lighting my lamp. Some type of a
thing which is not about a transaction and a transfer of funds.
There, there's no מעילה me'ilah בשוגג beshogeg because the sale is void.
The only time there's מעילה me'ilah. בשוגג b'shogeg. and you would bring
a קרבן בשוגג korban b'shogeg is when you actually directly benefited from
הקדש. hekdesh. So benefit from הקדש בשוגג, hekdesh b'shogeg, that's the case
of שוגג, shogeg, that's the case of מעילה, me'ilah that's the case,
you know, that maybe we can talk about the object going out
לחולין l'chulin if there's anything left of that object. But spending the
money, that would always be a void sale and that would never
be מעילה me'ila, בשוגג Beshogeg by Rabbi Meir. So interpreting the reason
it doesn't work is it's not a special, very limited case of
בגדי כהונה. bigdei kehuna. Fundamentally for Rabbi Meir, you if you had
known you wouldn't have done it, the sale is void, there's no
קידושין, Kiddushin, there's no sale if you used the money, and therefore
there will never be מעילה me'ila by misuse of funds בשוגג b'shogeg
according to Rabbi Meir. The exact reverse of the standard. The standard
is classic מעילה me'ila is בשוגג, b'shogeg, misuse of funds, and מזיד
meizid actually is, it does not go out לחולין. l'chulin. He's the
exact reverse. Okay, so let's continue now. The גמרא Gemara says like
this. Okay. Now that we've established we're back to, I mean it's
an extreme position but at least it's more stable, like we get
it. Okay, this real, this huge חידוש chiddush of Rabbi Meir. Let's
figure out how we פסקן pasken about all this stuff. So אמר
רב אדא בר אהבה, Amar Rav Adda bar Ahava, you'll be very
happy now, the rest of the דף daf is all how do
we פסקן. pasken. Okay, אמר רב אדא בר אהבה הלכה כרבי מאיר
במעשר, Amar Rav Adda bar Ahava halacha k'Rabbi Meir b'ma'aser, we rule
like Rabbi Meir by מעשר. ma'aser. Remember מעשר, ma'aser, you can't marry
a woman with מעשר שני ma'aser sheini money according to Rabbi Meir
because it's ממון גבוה, mamon gavo'ah, right? It's God's money, it's not
your money. Rabbi Yehuda disagreed. So we rule like Rabbi Meir by
מעשר, ma'aser, that it's always God's money and you can never use
it for קידושי אישה. kiddushei isha. Okay, הואיל וסתם לן תנא כוותיה
Ho'il v'stam lan tanna k'vaseih because we have a סתם משנה stam
Mishnah like him. והלכה כרבי יהודה בהקדש, V'halacha k'Rabbi Yehuda b'hekdesh, we
rule like Rabbi Yehuda by הקדש, hekdesh, which is the classic position
of הקדש. hekdesh. שוגג Shogeg it goes out לחולין l'chulin and the
woman is מתקדשת, miskadeshet, and מזיד meizid it does not because it
doesn't go out לחולין. l'chulin. Okay, וכרבי יהודה בהקדש הואיל וסתם לן
תנא כוותיה V'kh'Rabbi Yehuda b'hekdesh ho'il v'stam lan tanna k'vaseih because we
have a סתם משנה stam Mishnah like Rabbi Yehuda in the הקדש
hekdesh case. And now we're going to look at the סתם משניות
stam Mishnayot that support each of these positions. So now we're going
to go back to מעשר ma'aser for a minute. Rabbi, what just
me according to Rabbi, I know that the הלכה halacha is not
like according to Rabbi Meir, but it's like according to Rabbi Meir
if you were trying to be מקדש m'kadesh a woman using, using
coins rather than some object that you would get הנאה hana'ah from,
would that work, or does he make that distinction? No, I understand,
if you're trying to do it by a transaction, it doesn't work
because the sale is void. No matter what you use, no matter
what object? Right, right, yeah, correct. I mean it doesn't matter what
object you give, it's fundamentally about transferring ownership. Right, fine. So the
גמרא Gemara says like this. Okay, תניא כרבי מאיר במעשר, Tanya k'Rabbi
Meir b'ma'aser, how do we know we rule like Rabbi Meir by
מעשר ma'aser that מעשר שני ma'aser sheini is ממון גבוה mamon gavo'ah
and you can't use it to marry a woman? מאי היא? Mai
hi? דתנן, Detnan, כרם רבעי, kerem revai, what's the story about the
fourth-year fruit of a tree, right? The first three years are ערלה,
orlah, the fourth year it says קודש הלולים לה' kodesh hilulim l'Hashem
and we basically treat it like מעשר שני, ma'aser sheini, you bring
it to ירושלים Yerushalayim and eat it in ירושלים. Yerushalayim. We're going
to see there's a debate in בית שמאי ובית הלל Beit Shammai
u'Beit Hillel how much is it fully like מעשר שני. ma'aser sheini.
בית שמאי אומרים אין לו חומש, Beit Shammai omrim ein lo chomesh,
if you redeem the money, if you redeem it on money to
bring the money to ירושלים, Yerushalayim, you do not add a חומש,
chomesh, unlike מעשר שני. ma'aser sheini. ואין לו ביעור, V'ein lo bi'ur,
you don't have to get rid of it out of your house
if you haven't done anything with it by the third and sixth
year of the שמיטה shmita cycle, unlike מעשר שני ma'aser sheini where
you do. בית הלל אומרים יש לו. Beit Hillel omrim yeish lo.
No, it's like מעשר שני, ma'aser sheini, there's a חומש chomesh and
you have to get rid of it out of your house in
the third and sixth year. בית שמאי אומרים יש לו פרט ויש
לו עוללות, Beit Shammai omrim yeish lo perat v'yeish lo oleilot, there
are the gifts to the poor if we're talking here about כרם
רבעי, kerem revai, excuse me, it's about a vineyard specifically. So if
we're talking about the type of gifts to the poor, if you
drop some of the clusters of the grapes while you're harvesting it,
that's פרט, perat, עוללות oleilot is like unripe clusters, so those get
left to the poor. And so בית שמאי Beit Shammai says it
has the normal gifts to the poor. ובית הלל אומרים כולו לגת.
U'Beit Hillel omrim kulo l'gat. No, you don't leave anything to the
poor, you bring it all straight to the pressing vat, to the
wine vat. Okay, so meaning, but that's because בית שמאי Beit Shammai
treats it like normal fruit so it has those gifts, and בית
הלל Beit Hillel treats it more like מעשר שני, ma'aser sheini, and
מעשר שני, ma'aser sheini, you know... So basically, there's a clear debate
of בית שמאי Beit Shammai and בית הלל, Beit Hillel, you treat
it like מעשר שני Maaser Sheni or not. Okay. So, the גמרא
Gemara says like this: מאי טעמא דבית הלל? Mai Taama deBeis Hillel?
Why does בית הלל Beit Hillel treat it consistently like מעשר שני?
Maaser Sheni? גמירא, gmiira, they make a גזירה שוה, gezeirah shavah, קודש
קודש. kodesh kodesh. Here it says קודש הלולים להשם, Kodesh Hilulim L'Hashem,
and by מעשר maaser it says קודש להשם ממעשר. Kodesh L'Hashem miMaaser.
מה מעשר יש לו חומש ויש לו ביעור, Mah Maaser yesh lo
chomesh veyesh lo biur, the same way in מעשר שני Maaser Sheni
you add a fifth and you have to get it out of
your house in the third and sixth year, אף כרם רבעי יש
לו חומש ויש לו ביעור. aph Kerem Rivai yesh lo chomesh veyesh
lo biur. So same with כרם רבעי. Kerem Rivai. ובית שמאי לא
גמירי קודש קודש ממעשר, veBeit Shammai lo gmiiri kodesh kodesh miMaaser, they
don't make the link. Similarly, ובית הלל ממאן uBeis Hillel miman what,
בית הלל Beit Hillel says it's like מעשר שני, Maaser Sheni, they
say כמעשר. k'maaser. Okay. ובית הלל אמרי כמעשר. uBeit Hillel amri k'maaser.
כמאן סבירא להו? K'man sevirah lehu? Now because they say it's like
מעשר, maaser, they say you don't give the gifts to the poor,
you don't give פרט ועוללות. peret ve'olelot. So what is the logic
behind that, right? The logic why should just because it's מעשר maaser
exempt you from the gifts to the poor? Right, you got your
whole vineyard this year is its fourth year, why would you not
have to leave anything for the poor? Well, if מעשר maaser isn't
my money, if it's all God's money, then I don't have that
responsibility to leave it to the poor. If it's my money but
I have to bring it to ירושלים, Yerushalayim, then fine, still fundamentally
it's mine and I have the normal obligations. So that's exactly, since
בית הלל Beit Hillel says it's like מעשר שני, Maaser Sheni, that's
why they say you don't leave the gifts to the poor. That
proves a רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir position, that מעשר שני Maaser Sheni
is ממון גבוה. mammon gavoah. Okay, ומאן? veman? What? Could the poor
be doing the איבה eivah if בית שמאי Beit Shammai no, they
would bring it to ירושלים, Yerushalayim, the same way I would bring
it to ירושלים, Yerushalayim, that's okay, that's what בית שמאי Beit Shammai
would say. בית שמאי Beit Shammai would say you leave it to
the poor, and they have it, and they can they bring it
to ירושלים, Yerushalayim, but there's a תנא tanna that says make sure
yeah, this is all כרם רבעי, Kerem Rivai, so take it at
your own risk, it's כרם רבעי. Kerem Rivai. Okay, ובית הלל אמרי
כמעשר. uBeit Hillel amri k'maaser. כמאן סבירא להו? K'man sevirah lehu? Who
do they hold like? אי כרבי יהודה, Ee k'Rabbi Yehuda, if they
hold like רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, אמאי כולו לגת? amai kullo lagat?
Why does it all go to the wine vat? הא אמר מעשר
ממון הדיוט הוא. Ha amar maaser mammon hedyot hu. It's like your
it's your money with an obligation to eat it in ירושלים, Yerushalayim,
but it's your money and therefore it would you should have to
give the gifts to the poor. אלא לאו כרבי מאיר? Ella lav
k'Rabbi Meir? It must be like רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, so you
see, it's as רש"י Rashi points out, סתם משנה stam mishna is
רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir means בית הלל. Beit Hillel. בית הלל Beit
Hillel counts as a סתם משנה stam mishna because there the הלכה
halacha is like. So if בית הלל Beit Hillel presumes the position
of רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, which is pretty funny because רבי מאיר
Rabbi Meir and רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda came later and they were
all obviously from the בית הלל Beit Hillel school, but nevertheless the
גמרא Gemara says it's clearly seems to be the presumption of בית
הלל Beit Hillel and therefore we're going to side with רבי מאיר,
Rabbi Meir, מעשר שני Maaser Sheni is ממון גבוה. mammon gavoah. Now
the גמרא Gemara just raises an objection. The גמרא Gemara says, where
were we? Oh, I'm sorry, no, no, won't raise objection, that's the
end here. So now we're going to so that proves that we
פסקינן paskin by מעשר שני Maaser Sheni ממון גבוה. mammon gavoah. Now
we're going to move to prove that we פסקינן paskin and this
will be the easier thing as you can imagine that by הקדש
hekdesh I don't know, easier, but whatever, it's everything we've ever seen
when we've seen מעילה, me'ilah, that by מעילה me'ilah we rule like
רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. There is מעילה me'ilah when the money is
misused בשוגג beshogeg and there's not מעילה me'ilah when it's misused במזיד.
bemezid. So let's just read one ברייתא braita about that and then
we'll continue with that tomorrow. Okay. כרבי יהודה בהקדש מאי היא? KeRabbi
Yehuda behekdesh mai hi? Where do we see that we rule like
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda by הקדש? hekdesh? דתנן, detnan, we taught in
the משנה, mishna, שילח ביד פיקח. shilach beyad pikeiach. You go ahead
you went ahead and you had funds, okay, they were הקדש hekdesh
funds, you didn't realize, and you sent somebody who was a not
a minor and not somebody who is of not right mind, you
know, somebody who was a a a fit person, right, to and
you went and you gave him the funds so he was a
שליח shaliach to go ahead and to spend the money. Okay, go
to the storekeeper, buy me buy me a dozen eggs. Okay, ונזכר
עד שלא הגיע אצל חנווני. venizkar ad shelo higia eitzel chanvani. Before
he got to the storekeeper, he remembered, "Oh my God, they're הקדש
hekdesh funds." So in that case, חנווני מועל לכשיצא. chanvani mo'el leksheyotzi.
The חנווני chanvani when he gets the money, okay, he actually is
מועל mo'el if he goes ahead and he misuses the money. Now
actually the גמרא Gemara says when it discusses this משנה mishna that
both me and the שליח shaliach remembered, because if I remembered and
the שליח shaliach didn't, the שליח shaliach would be מועל. mo'el. But
both of us remembered, so both of us were במזיד, bemezid, so
the money did not יצא לחולין, yeitzei lechullin, and then when the
חנווני chanvani who's unaware spends it, it is יצא לחולין. yeitzei lechullin.
So that's exactly this. The guy who's שוגג shogeg is מועל mo'el
and it's יצא לחולין, yeitzei lechullin, the guy who remembered, it's not
יצא לחולין. yeitzei lechullin. Okay? So עד שלא הגיע אצל חנווני חנווני
מועל לכשיצא. ad shelo higia eitzel chanvani chanvani mo'el leksheyotzi. So you
see that we rule like רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. Okay, so that's
why we rule those two ways. Okay, so we'll pick up tomorrow
to question if all the משניות mishnayot all work within that approach,
but right now we are saying that we rule that מעשר שני
Maaser Sheni is ממון גבוה mammon gavoah like רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir
and we rule that הקדש hekdesh מעילה me'ilah occurs בשוגג beshogeg when
the money is spent בשוגג beshogeg and the money does not go
out לחולין lechullin when it's spent במזיד, bemezid, the exact that's רבי
יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, the exact reverse of רבי מאיר's Rabbi Meir position.
All right. All right. Now the גמרא *Gemara* moves to a third
question and asks the following. אמר ליה *Amar leih* רב פפא *Rav
Pappa* לאביי *l'Abaye*. רב פפא *Rav Pappa* asks a question to אביי
*Abaye*. We see the following. According to the משנה *Mishnah* in מעילה
*Me'ilah*, and it's basically the reverse of our משנה *Mishnah*, why? If
someone takes money of הקדש *Hekdesh* and he gives it to a
בלן *balan*, a bathhouse keeper. Okay? If he gave it to him
בשוגג *b'shogeg*, unintentionally, then the donor is מועל *mo'el*, המועל *hamo'el*, the
money becomes חולין *chullin*. But if he gave it במזיד *b'meizid*, if
he gave it intentionally, then the money remains הקדש *Hekdesh*, the money
is not חולין *chullin*. Now let's think. That makes no sense. The
משנה *Mishnah* in מעילה *Me'ilah* says if he pays the בלן *balan*
for the bathhouse using הקדש *Hekdesh* money. If it's בשוגג *b'shogeg*, the
money becomes חולין *chullin*. If it's במזיד *b'meizid*, the money does not
become חולין *chullin*. Contrast that with our משנה *Mishnah*. In our משנה
*Mishnah*, when it comes to the קידושין *kiddushin* of a woman, the
משנה *Mishnah* says if a man gives הקדש *Hekdesh* to a woman
for קידושין *kiddushin* במזיד *b'meizid*, the money becomes חולין *chullin* and she
is מקודשת *mekudeshet*. Why do we say במזיד *b'meizid* it becomes חולין
*chullin* regarding קידושין *kiddushin*, while במזיד *b'meizid* it does not become חולין
*chullin* regarding the bathhouse keeper? That's the question that רב פפא *Rav
Pappa* is asking.